<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on </title>
    <link>http://lseem.xyz/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><atom:link href="http://lseem.xyz/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A Nice and Satisfying Way to Look at Connections</title>
      <link>http://lseem.xyz/articles/a-nice-and-satisfying-way-to-look-at-connections/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lseem.xyz/articles/a-nice-and-satisfying-way-to-look-at-connections/</guid>
      <description>Introduction It is difficult to find this rather nice way of looking at connections in differential geometry textbooks. Perhaps because it is not so much of use in Riemannian geometry (where your connection is basically always the Levi-Cività connection so in fact all the curvature is induced by the metric). But still, I think it&amp;rsquo;s nice and prepares the student for further study in geometry.
In this article I&amp;rsquo;ll explain two Nice and Satisfying Things about this point of view.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Second Year Essay</title>
      <link>http://lseem.xyz/projects/second-year-essay/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lseem.xyz/projects/second-year-essay/</guid>
      <description>In my second year I wrote The Isoperimetric Problem: Geometry and Analysis and I guess I&amp;rsquo;m quite proud of it. I think the markers didn&amp;rsquo;t like the fact that I didn&amp;rsquo;t provide pin-point references, so sorry! Although, below is a list of some references which I think you might want to take a look at:
 Felix Bernstein. “Über die isoperimetrische Eigenschaft des Kreises auf der Kugeloberfläche und in der Ebene”.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summer Research Project 2020</title>
      <link>http://lseem.xyz/projects/summer-research-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lseem.xyz/projects/summer-research-project/</guid>
      <description>Over the summer I did a project in free boundary minimal annuli in the unit ball. Specifically, I studied an object called the critical catenoid, which is the only known example of a free boundary minimal annulus in the unit ball. I made a poster.
This is an image I made of the critical catenoid with POV-Ray. I can&amp;rsquo;t seem to get the lighting or material just how I want it.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
