<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on </title>
    <link>http://lseem.xyz/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://lseem.xyz/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Chain Complex</title>
      <link>http://lseem.xyz/wiki/chain-complex/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lseem.xyz/wiki/chain-complex/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Definition A chain complex is a sequence of abelian groups \( C_n \) (one for each \( n\in\mathbb{Z} \)) together with maps \( d_n:C_n\to C_{n-1} \) called *differentials* such that \( d_nd_{n+1}=0 \) for every \( n\in\mathbb{Z} \).
Lemmata References and Notes  This article is based on a lecture course on algebraic topology given at Warwick by Chris Lazda.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chain Homotopy</title>
      <link>http://lseem.xyz/wiki/chain-homotopy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lseem.xyz/wiki/chain-homotopy/</guid>
      <description>Introduction The motivation for the concept of a chain homotopy is to abstract the prism operator to a more algebraic setting.
Note that this diagram is not a &amp;ldquo;commutative diagram&amp;rdquo;, but since \(f\) and \(g\) are chain maps, there are two commutative &amp;ldquo;sub&amp;rdquo;-diagrams.
Definition If \(C_\bullet\) and \(D_\bullet\) are chain complexes, and \(f,g:C_\bullet\to D_\bullet\) are chain maps, then a *chain homotopy* from \(f\) to \(g\) is a colleciton of homomorphisms \(P:C_n\to D_{n+1}\) such that for all \(n\),</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Homotopy Invariance</title>
      <link>http://lseem.xyz/wiki/homotopy-invariance/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lseem.xyz/wiki/homotopy-invariance/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Homotopy invariance is a key theorem from algebraic topology. It says that if two maps are homotopic then they induce the same singular homology homomorphism. The prerequisite notions for this theorem are singular homology and the prism operator.
Statement and Proof Theorem: Let \(X\) and \(Y\) be topological spaces. If \(f,g:X\to Y\) are homotopic, then their induced singular homology homomorphisms are equal:
\[ f_* = g_* : H_n(X) \to H_n(Y).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Prism Operator</title>
      <link>http://lseem.xyz/wiki/prism-operator/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lseem.xyz/wiki/prism-operator/</guid>
      <description>Introduction The motivation for studying the prism operator comes from proving homotopy invariance. The prism operator takes a singular n-chain and forms a singular (n+1)-chain from it by passing the n-chain through a homotopy, creating &amp;ldquo;prisms&amp;rdquo; in the process.
As an introduction, we first study the 2-dimensional case. Let \(X\) and \(Y\) be topological spaces, \(H:X\times I\to Y\) be a homotopy, and \(\sigma:\Delta^2\to X\) be a singular 2-simplex in \(X\). We can then form a prism by passing \(\sigma\) through the homotopy:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Towards Quadratic Reciprocity</title>
      <link>http://lseem.xyz/posts/towards-quadratic-reciprocity-2-eulers-criterion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lseem.xyz/posts/towards-quadratic-reciprocity-2-eulers-criterion/</guid>
      <description>In this blog post, we continue where we left off in order to derive Euler&amp;rsquo;s Criterion. First, we define some key terms that will be important to us.
Definition (quadratic residue): Let \(m\in\mathbb{N}\), and let \(a\in\mathbb{Z}\) be coprime to \(m\). We say that \(a\) is a quadratic residue modulo \(m\) if there exists \(x\in\mathbb{Z}\) such that \(x^2\equiv_m a\). We say that \(a\) is a quadratic non-residue modulo \(m\) if there does not exist any such \(x\).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Towards Quadratic Reciprocity</title>
      <link>http://lseem.xyz/posts/towards-quadratic-reciprocity-1-two-square-roots/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lseem.xyz/posts/towards-quadratic-reciprocity-1-two-square-roots/</guid>
      <description>(NB: This post was uploaded well after the exam, as these count as my own notes and wished to use them for the open book exam.)
I have a number theory exam coming up, and I really need to understand the famous Law of Quadratic Reciprocity. In the following series of blogposts, I will outline a proof of this Law, beginning with the Two Square Roots Lemma, then moving on to Euler&amp;rsquo;s Criterion (which we derive as a corollary of a more general theorem), after which we shall prove Gauss&#39; Lemma (one of his many&amp;hellip;), and then finally arrive at the Law.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Tracing in \(S^3\) or \(H^3\) (or more general 3-Manifolds?)</title>
      <link>http://lseem.xyz/posts/ray-tracing-in-s3-or-h3-or-more-general-3-manifolds/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lseem.xyz/posts/ray-tracing-in-s3-or-h3-or-more-general-3-manifolds/</guid>
      <description>I have a project in mind, and this project is to write a ray tracer for non-Euclidean geometries. While ultimately I am looking for full generality and would like to ray trace on any sufficiently regular 3-manifold, I will modestly set my first thousand-mile stone to ray tracing in the 3-sphere or in hyperbolic 3-space.
This project is mainly inspired by the film Interstellar, whose visual effects production studio Double Negative wrote a renderer in order to render the black hole in the film.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Second Year Essay</title>
      <link>http://lseem.xyz/projects/second-year-essay/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lseem.xyz/projects/second-year-essay/</guid>
      <description>{{ .Date := 0 }}
In my second year I wrote The Isoperimetric Problem: Geometry and Analysis and I guess I&amp;rsquo;m quite proud of it. I think the markers didn&amp;rsquo;t like the fact that I didn&amp;rsquo;t provide pin-point references, so sorry! Although, below is a list of some references which I think you might want to take a look at:
 Felix Bernstein. “Über die isoperimetrische Eigenschaft des Kreises auf der Kugeloberfläche und in der Ebene”.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summer Research Project 2020</title>
      <link>http://lseem.xyz/projects/summer-research-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lseem.xyz/projects/summer-research-project/</guid>
      <description>Over the summer I did a project in free boundary minimal annuli in the unit ball. Specifically, I studied an object called the critical catenoid, which is the only known example of a free boundary minimal annulus in the unit ball. I made a poster. </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
