<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-09-15T11:49:39+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">The Myth of the Evil Terrorist</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/09/09/the-myth-of-the-evil-terrorist.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Myth of the Evil Terrorist" /><published>2019-09-09T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-09-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/09/09/the-myth-of-the-evil-terrorist</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/09/09/the-myth-of-the-evil-terrorist.html">&lt;p&gt;In recent years Islamic terrorist attacks in Europe have somewhat taken over
the media discourse. Certainly more people are killed in road accidents than in
terrorist attacks; in the UK between 2000 and 2013, there were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.start.umd.edu/gtd/&quot;&gt;89
fatalities&lt;/a&gt; due to terrorist attacks (of all
types - not just Islamic) but there were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/annual-road-fatalities&quot;&gt;38,316
fatalities&lt;/a&gt;
in Great Britain due to road accidents in the same period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such a comparison of numbers is on the surface valid yet is often deemed
erroneously reductionist, simplistic, cynical, and clichéd. Road accidents are
usually just that - accidents, with no malice or specific desire to kill. If
someone were to be killed in a road accident, there is a sense in that this
person was just unlucky; another number in the statistic. Terrorists, on the
other hand, set out to kill. If someone were to be killed by a terrorist then
there is a motive behind the death; the terrorist motive. In the road accident
the morals of the participants play no role, but in the terrorist attack the
clash of morals of the terrorist and the victims is usually the premise of the
attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The media of the victims therefore portray the terrorist as evil; the media of
the terrorists likewise portray the victims as evil. Both of these are nice
stories that resonate with our sense of narrative. It is given (to the intended
audience of this post) that anti-extremist campainers are highly moral. Let me
be controversial for a moment: Islamic terrorists are some of the most moral
people in our society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moderately religious and atheist people tend to forget the power of belief. To
really &lt;em&gt;believe&lt;/em&gt; something is to &lt;em&gt;hold true in one’s mind&lt;/em&gt;. If you believe that
you were sent on a mission by God to establish the Caliphate, then it is
perhaps the most moral thing to do is precisely what the terrorists do. It
would be immoral to sit around and do nothing and not help establish such a
Caliphate. But you don’t believe in the establishment of the Caliphate, so you
think that the terrorists are immoral. Islamic terrorists have a fundamentally
different conception of reality, and it is this clash of &lt;em&gt;conceptions&lt;/em&gt; that
leads to violence. Similarly a conspiracy theorist believes supposedly “crazy”
things about the world, while you (perhaps) do not. The difference between you
and a consipracy theorist is the same nature of that between you and an islamic
terrorist, and the only distinction between the two is one of scale. Yet you do
not regard the conspiracy theorist as evil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When was the last time you went on a political march? Were you shouting outside
Parliament yesterday to defend the rights of EU citizens post-Brexit? If you
were, then your belief that it is moral that the rights of EU citizens be
upheld post-brexit led you to that political march, and you were behaving
morally. In the same way, the terrorist has beliefs about morality that lead
them to behave in a certain way. The poltical activist and the terrorist can be
just as moral as each other; it is their beliefs that lead to problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beliefs influence behaviour, and so it is not the holder of the beliefs that
are immoral. In order to stop Islamic terrorist attacks, we must stop the
demonisation of terrorists and we must view them as victims of a set of
beliefs. Having been deradicalised, former Islamic terrorists can play a highly
postive role in our society due to their highly moral nature. But what makes
our set of beliefs any more moral than those of Islamic terrorists? Why instead
shouldn’t they be “de-Westernising” us into extremist Islam?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which beliefs lead to the action that leads to the least human suffering? This
is a difficult question to answer but one we can entertain. It may seem obvious
that the beliefs of an Islamic terrorist lead to more human suffering that
those of a moderate Muslim or a Catholic. It is in this way that we “prefer”
the belief systems of a moderate Muslim or Catholic. Furthermore, it may also
be the case that secular beliefs lead to less human suffering than moderate
Islamic or Catholic beliefs. In this way we can rank belief systems, and our
moral framework need only one axiom: minimise the amount of human suffering. A
one-axiom moral framework is necessarily the most parsimonious of all moral
frameworks, and it is certainly more parsimonious than any religious one.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="politics" /><category term="terrorism" /><category term="philosophy" /><summary type="html">In recent years Islamic terrorist attacks in Europe have somewhat taken over the media discourse. Certainly more people are killed in road accidents than in terrorist attacks; in the UK between 2000 and 2013, there were 89 fatalities due to terrorist attacks (of all types - not just Islamic) but there were 38,316 fatalities in Great Britain due to road accidents in the same period.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Criticism of the Fine-Tuning Argument</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/04/22/criticism-fta.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Criticism of the Fine-Tuning Argument" /><published>2018-04-22T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-04-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/04/22/criticism-fta</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/04/22/criticism-fta.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This essay serves as a criticism of the Fine-Tuning Argument (henceforth, for brevity, referred to using the acronym FTA) for the existence of God.
In order to do so we recognise FTA’s reliance on the notion of Common Sense.
We then analyse the notion of Common Sense, and find where it is or is not valid.
Having found that Common Sense is only valid from certain perspectives, we then show that the FTA, relying on Common Sense, is made from a perspective where Common Sense is not valid.
Therefore the FTA is not a valid argument for the existence of God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-fine-tuning-argument-for-the-existence-of-god&quot;&gt;The Fine-Tuning Argument for the Existence of God&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We begin by outlining the FTA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The constants of the universe, which are called “constants” by their virtue of being unit-independent and are found by physicists using the method of science (that method viewed by us to be currently the most effective known for measuring reality) are such that if changed even very slightly outside the limits of their experimental errors then the resulting reality would be a very different one, indeed one in which we would not exist.
It is therefore highly unlikely that these constants became so finely-tuned
through chance, and it is therefore reasonable to assume that God fixed those
constants, and therefore God exists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first sentence, talking about the changing of physical constants, is one which is irrefutable.
If we create a universe which follows the same laws of logic as our current one, and it is therefore valid to use mathematical methods as is common in science, but this universe has differing constants, then it has been shown mathematically that, for example, the universe would instantaneously collapse, or that atoms would not form, or that, stars would never form, etc.
This is what we shall refer to as a scientific fact - given our current theory (which we know for sure is incomplete), then changing the physical constants results in a universe in which humans would not exist, and indeed that which we currently regard as life would not exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the criticisms are from the second sentence, which talks about conclusions from this scientific fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second sentence talks about a notion of things being “unlikely” and probability.
This is very vaguely defined.
When we talk about probability, we have a few prerequisites which are well defined.
Firstly, we have a set of all possible events.
Secondly, each event is associated with a probability of that event occurring.
Thirdly, we have the requirement that the summation of the probability of each event, over all events, be equal to 1.
In this case, all the possible events are all the possible different unique universes defined by their various physical constants.
Crucially, we do not have probabilities associated with each universe - the likelihood of the existence of each universe.
It is therefore useless to talk about the likelihood of the existence of this universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How might we find out the probability of each universe existing?
Usually, we would use science.
We would on the one hand model the situation mathematically, and then on the other hand verify this experimentally.
In the case of throwing a die, for example, would model this mathematically.
We assume that the die is a cube, and therefore has geometric symmetry resulting in no particular preference for each side.
Therefore the probability of the die landing on one particular face is equal to the probability of another face.
But there are only 6 faces, so there are only 6 events, and the probabilities of all the events must sum to 1.
Therefore the probability of the die landing on each face is \( \frac{1}{6} \).
We then verify this experimentally, throwing hundreds of thousands of dice and counting out of all the times that the dice are thrown, how many times each side turns up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, while we might come up with some sort of mathematical theory as to what the probability of each universe existing, we have no way of measuring whether this theory is true.
We therefore have an unverifiable hypothesis.
Therefore the hypotheses, “the probability of a universe having the physical
constants of this one is 1, and the probability of a universe having different
physical constants is 0”, and “the probability of a universe having the
physical constants of this one is \(\frac{1}{2}\), and the probability of a
universe having different physical constants is \(\frac{1}{2}\)” are both as valid as the other.
The only hypothesis we know to be weak (read “false”) given the assumption that
this universe exists (and we could verify this experimentally), is that “the
probability of a universe having the physical constants of this one is 0”, because then this universe would not exist - but, by experimental evidence, it does exist, therefore the hypothesis is weak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FTA assumes a uniform distribution of universes - it assumes that all possible universes are as likely as each other - because it is natural and normal to do so.
It is Common Sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We claim that Common Sense is not valid when talking about universes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;common-sense&quot;&gt;Common Sense&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Common Sense is the ability to understand that which is shared by nearly all people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We note that even the definition of Common Sense is vague, and this is one of the fundamental flaws of Common Sense.
Due to the vague definition of Common Sense (one might even say that the definition of Common Sense is just Common Sense - everyone knows it), it is difficult to argue against.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not, however, impossible to analyse the phenomenon.
We start with an example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Common Sense tells us that the Earth is flat.
For people who have grown up thinking that the Earth is flat, learning that the Earth is roughly spherically shaped is absurd.
Note that in order to survive and thrive, it is not necessary to know that the Earth is round.
This is because the roundness of the Earth has very little impact on our everyday lives.
And from a human perspective, the Earth looks very flat.
As your perspective gets smaller and smaller, the earth looks flatter and flatter, and critically, it becomes experimentally valid to claim that the Earth is flat.
For a human, approximating a sphere to a flat surface is fine, because the curvature of the Earth is so slight from our perspective that it does not matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using science, we can extend our perspectives to beyond the limits of that of a human.
We use creativity to create mathematical models of the world around us.
We use creativity, logic, and mathematics, to analyse these models and come up with predictions about the universe.
We use creativity to devise experiments to test the predictions of those models and try to disprove them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, we use science to infer things about the universe which are beyond our direct human perspective.
A flat-Earth theory works, until you devise a clever experiment which tests predictions of the flat-Earth theory, to show that a round-Earth theory works better than a flat-Earth theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Common Sense only works for things that are in a human perspective.
For things outside a human perspective, Common Sense is not valid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Universes are outside human perspectives.
We have shown that Common Sense is not valid from outside a human perspective.
The FTA relies on Common Sense.
But the FTA deals with universes, which are outside the human perspective.
Therefore since Common Sense is invalid when dealing with universes, then the FTA is invalid when dealing with universes.
Therefore the FTA is invalid.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="philosophy" /><category term="theology" /><summary type="html">Abstract This essay serves as a criticism of the Fine-Tuning Argument (henceforth, for brevity, referred to using the acronym FTA) for the existence of God. In order to do so we recognise FTA’s reliance on the notion of Common Sense. We then analyse the notion of Common Sense, and find where it is or is not valid. Having found that Common Sense is only valid from certain perspectives, we then show that the FTA, relying on Common Sense, is made from a perspective where Common Sense is not valid. Therefore the FTA is not a valid argument for the existence of God.</summary></entry></feed>