<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on </title>
    <link>http://lseem.xyz/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://lseem.xyz/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>New Videos on Tangent Spaces and Submanifolds</title>
      <link>http://lseem.xyz/posts/new-videos-on-tangent-spaces-and-submanifolds/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lseem.xyz/posts/new-videos-on-tangent-spaces-and-submanifolds/</guid>
      <description>I have uploaded two new videos for the Multivarible Calculus revision series about submanifolds (which you can find under Resources):
 Part 2 - Tangent Spaces Part 3 - Level Sets as Submanifolds  While the video on tangent spaces was relatively easy, the other video about level sets was much harder. It is a more difficult topic to explain, and it took me a while to find the right picture which will give everything in detail.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revision Videos for Multivariable Calculus at Warwick</title>
      <link>http://lseem.xyz/posts/revision-videos-for-multivariable-calculus-at-warwick/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lseem.xyz/posts/revision-videos-for-multivariable-calculus-at-warwick/</guid>
      <description>I have in the past few days uploaded some revision videos for the Multivariable Calculus course at Warwick (2020 &amp;ndash; 2021) taught by Mario Micallef. You can find them under Resources. Currently, they contain references to &amp;ldquo;the notes&amp;rdquo;. I may update them at some later point, removing all such references.
The point of the videos is not to go over the rigour and the proofs, but to give a higher level and intuitive view of the course.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Towards Quadratic Reciprocity</title>
      <link>http://lseem.xyz/posts/towards-quadratic-reciprocity-2-eulers-criterion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lseem.xyz/posts/towards-quadratic-reciprocity-2-eulers-criterion/</guid>
      <description>TODO: Migrate to wiki
In this blog post, we continue where we left off in order to derive Euler&amp;rsquo;s Criterion. First, we define some key terms that will be important to us.
Definition (quadratic residue): Let \(m\in\mathbb{N}\), and let \(a\in\mathbb{Z}\) be coprime to \(m\). We say that \(a\) is a quadratic residue modulo \(m\) if there exists \(x\in\mathbb{Z}\) such that \(x^2\equiv_m a\). We say that \(a\) is a quadratic non-residue modulo \(m\) if there does not exist any such \(x\).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Towards Quadratic Reciprocity</title>
      <link>http://lseem.xyz/posts/towards-quadratic-reciprocity-1-two-square-roots/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lseem.xyz/posts/towards-quadratic-reciprocity-1-two-square-roots/</guid>
      <description>TODO: Migrate to wiki
(NB: This post was uploaded well after the exam, as these count as my own notes and wished to use them for the open book exam.)
I have a number theory exam coming up, and I really need to understand the famous Law of Quadratic Reciprocity. In the following series of blogposts, I will outline a proof of this Law, beginning with the Two Square Roots Lemma, then moving on to Euler&amp;rsquo;s Criterion (which we derive as a corollary of a more general theorem), after which we shall prove Gauss&#39; Lemma (one of his many&amp;hellip;), and then finally arrive at the Law.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Tracing in \(S^3\) or \(H^3\) (or more general 3-Manifolds?)</title>
      <link>http://lseem.xyz/posts/ray-tracing-in-s3-or-h3-or-more-general-3-manifolds/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lseem.xyz/posts/ray-tracing-in-s3-or-h3-or-more-general-3-manifolds/</guid>
      <description>I have a project in mind, and this project is to write a ray tracer for non-Euclidean geometries. While ultimately I am looking for full generality and would like to ray trace on any sufficiently regular 3-manifold, I will modestly set my first thousand-mile stone to ray tracing in the 3-sphere or in hyperbolic 3-space.
This project is mainly inspired by the film Interstellar, whose visual effects production studio Double Negative wrote a renderer in order to render the black hole in the film.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
